<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L139.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert, October 12th, 1950</title>
<title type="main">Carta de William F. Schubert a Santos Baros Schubert, 12 de octubre, 1950</title>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
<name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name> 
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L139.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1950-10-12">October 12th, 1950</date>
<extent>2 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>2 typed pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>2 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p>Media: black ink</p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1950-10-12"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#af">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.522.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Camp 67</addrLine></address>
<dateline>12 Oct 1950</dateline>

<salute>My Darling Wife,</salute>
</opener>

<p>Sure was glad to receive another swell letter from you today; sure makes me feel better when I hear that you and Billy are OK and thinking of me.  Darling, I am missing you more every day.  I think that we will be done here by next week-end so will meet you on the 22nd in Lincoln.</p>

<p>Have sure been busy yesterday and today. I had a check for a waiter that was suppose to go to work in Lincoln Depot and he owed me some money so I took it into Lincoln but he wasn’t there yesterday. I rode the train in; left here at 12:15 P.M. and got to Lincoln at 4:15 P.M.; then, I drove back to camp. I picked-up some clothes for the timekeeper; got my pants from the cleaner; moved everything into the new trailer, so all I have to do in scrub the Prairie Schooner Sunday. The folks are going to Aunt Mary’s Sunday so I’ll have to be in Lincoln if I can get some good help together by then.</p>

<p>All my waiters and the second cook were drinking today; so I’m going to send them all in. One waiter left and haven’t seen him yet this evening and the second cook couldn’t do his work; but he has a steak dinner ordered for 7:30 for us at this good eating place so I’m trying to get my work done and a letter to you before I go. It’s already 7;10P.M.</p>

<p>My checks were a little under $300.00 this month; but I paid the Bank $125.00. If you need some money let me know otherwise I’ll not send any for you to have to carry home.</p>

<p>We had two more gandies get hurt today and there is no Doctor here so the timekeeper hasto take them to Falls City. Tomorrow is pay day for the men so we’ll have more fun. I have to close my books tomorrow too as the 15th is Sunday; sure wish I could keep open this week-end as I know the men will want cigarettes to sell.</p>

<fw>OVER</fw>

<pb facs="shan_l.523.jpg"/>

<p>Darling, I’ll write more tomorrow night; Remember I love you very much so write often.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Always yours</salute>                    
<signed>Bill</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>Love to you<lb/>
&amp; Billy<lb/></p>
</postscript>

</div1>
 
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">  

 <pb facs="shan_l.522.jpg"/>

  <opener>
   <address><addrLine>Campamento 67</addrLine></address>
   <dateline>12 de Octubre de 1950</dateline>
   
   <salute>Mi querida esposa,</salute>
  </opener>
 
 <p>De veras que me alegró recibir hoy una bonita carta tuya. De veras que me hace sentir mejor el enterarme de que tú y Billy están bien y que piensan en mí. Querida, te extraño más cada día. Creo que terminaremos el próximo fin de semana, así que alcanzaré el día 22 en Lincoln.</p>
 
 <p>De veras que he estado ocupado ayer y hoy. Tenía un cheque para un mesero que debía ir a trabajar en la estación de Lincoln y me debía algo de dinero así que lleve el cheque a Lincoln pero no estuvo ayer. Tomé en tren. Salí de aquí a las 12:15 PM y llegue a Lincoln a las 4:15 PM, y después maneje de regreso al campamento. Recogí una ropa para el cronometrador, recogí mis pantalones de la tintorería, moví todo al nuevo tráiler, así que lo único que tengo que hacer es restregar el Prairie Schooner el domingo. Mis papás van a ir a casa de la tía Mary el domingo, así que tendré que estar en Lincoln si puedo conseguir quien me ayude para entonces.</p> 
 
 <p>Todos los meseros y mi segundo cocinero estuvieron bebiendo hoy, así que los voy a regresar. Uno de los meseros se fue y todavía no lo he visto hoy en la noche, y el segundo cocinero no podía trabajar, pero ordenó una cena con carne para las 7:30 en un buen lugar para cenar, así que estoy tratando de acabar mi trabajo y una carta para ti antes de irme. Ya son las 7:10 PM.</p>
 
 <p>Mis cheques me llegaron por poco menos de $300.00 este mes, pero pague $125.00 al banco. Si necesitas algo de dinero dime. Si no, no te mandaré nada para que no tengas que cargarlo de vuelta a casa.</p>
 
 <p>Hoy se hirieron otros dos gandies y aquí no hay un doctor, así que el cronometrador los tiene que llevar hasta Falls City. Mañana es día de pago para los hombres, así que nos divertiremos más. También tengo que cerrar mi contabilidad mañana porque el 15 es domingo. Mu hubiera gustado tener abiertos este fin de semana porque que sé que van a querer cigarros para vender.</p>
 
 <fw>OTRO LADO</fw>
 
 <pb facs="shan_l.523.jpg"/>
 
 <p>Querida, te escribiré más mañana en la noche. Recuerda que te amo mucho, así que escribe a menudo.</p>
 
 <closer>
  <salute>Siempre tuyo</salute>                    
  <signed>Bill</signed>
 </closer>
 
 <postscript>
  <p>Mi amor para ti y para Billy</p>
 </postscript>
 
</div1>
 
</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>