<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L124.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to John J. Schubert and Gwendoly Schubert, March 17, 1942</title>
<title type="main">Carta de William F. Schubert a John J. Schubert and Gwendoly Schubert, 17 de marzo, 1942</title>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Mendell, Kate</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
<name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>  
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L124.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to John J. Schubert and Gwendoly Schubert</title>
<date when="1942-03-17">March 17, 1942</date>
<extent>4 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 typed pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p>Media: black ink</p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1942-03-17"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1942-03-17"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="jjs001">Schubert, John Jack</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="gs001">Schubert, Gwendoly</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#km">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.462.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Lincoln, Nebraska</addrLine></address>
<dateline>March 17, 1942</dateline>

<salute>Dear Folks,</salute>
</opener>

<p>I received your card and today I got your letter. Glad to hear from you.</p>
                
<p>I just wrote those men and told them that I already accepted a clerical job.</p>

<p>Jim was down tonight and we went up town for a while. I just got back and got those other letters written so am writing you so as to mail them all yet tonight. I mail them at the Depot.</p>

<p>Mr. Lollis left for Chicago tonight and will be back Thursday morning.</p>

<p>Last Saturday Mr. Lollis and I went up to Omaha. He saw some people in the afternoon, then we have a “chicken in the rough” for supper (half a chicken), after that we went to the Theatre and saw three shows and the KMA school was there. Maybe you heard the KMA program as it was broadcasted. Mr. Lollis paid for the diner and shows. When we got ready to come home it was quite disagreeable so he rent us a room

<pb facs="shan_l.463.jpg"/>

at the Tourist Tower cabins, so we stay there until Sunday morning then we came home. He let me drive going up and in Omaha.</p>

<p>I am getting along alright. I believe this job has a good future. Right now before the camp leaves we are cleaning up and getting ready to leave. Next week our groceries and supplies come in. Boy! you ought to see the order we made last night—4000lbs of sugar—300lbs powder sugar—300 lbs rasins and large amounts of everything. I will tell you all about the camp when I come home. I don’t know when that will be though.</p>

<p>I have to help with the groceries and supplies-keep and type reports-help in the commissary (place where we sell anything a man who works would buy-clothes-candy, etc.).</p>

<p>Last night we worked until 11:30—not very hard though.</p>

<p>You see I am working with the C.B.&amp;Q [Chicago, Burlington&amp;Quincy Railroad]. but with John J. Grier Co. with has these camps. We board and room the C.B.&amp;Q. employees for $8.75 a week.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.464.jpg"/>

 <p>There are only five of us here now, but there will be more than 200 when camp opens the 6th of April. We will be in Crete for about a week then go to St. Joe, then to Colo. Then Wisconsin and I don’t know where all from there as we work all lines of C.B.&amp;Q.</p>

<p>I think I told you I would get to drive his car some. It is a 1941 Studebaker Commander. He has $50,000 insurance on it, and he is going to have my name put on the insurance with his.</p>

<p>I have got a Royal portable typewriter to used.</p>

<p>Jim and I might come down some night or Sunday. I am planning on coming down to the Jr. Play with Jim that night.</p>

<p>We sure get plenty to eat here. Mr. Lollis goes uptown and buys the best of everything. We have meat for every meal, potatoes, bread, butter, and usual one or two vegetables besides. He buys rolls, cakes, etc.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.465.jpg"/>

<p>I think I will close for tonight, and go over and mail this. It is only about a block across to the Depot.</p>

<closer>
 <salute>Tell everybody Hello! Your son&amp;brother.,</salute>                    
 <signed>William F. Schubert</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>P.S. We have our own light plant which is 110 volts, a car for kitchen, dinner cars, sleeping cars and everything including shower baths.</p>
<p>I got a letter back from the Civil Service. I got an average of 93.67 I think I will keep this job though even if I do get a change at C.S. before long.</p>
</postscript>     
 
</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.460.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>William F. Schubert</addrLine> 
<addrLine>P.O. Box 1444</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, Nebraska</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mr. and Mrs. John J. Schubert &amp; Family</addrLine>
<addrLine>Palmyra, Nebraska</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="note">
INFO ON<lb/>
STEEL GANG<lb/>
JOHN J. GRIER<lb/>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
LINCOLN, NEBR. TERM<lb/> 
TOUR 5<lb/>
MAR 17<lb/>
1942<lb/>
R.P.O.<lb/>
</ab>

</div1>

 <div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.462.jpg"/>
  
  <opener>
   <address><addrLine>Lincoln, Nebraska</addrLine></address>
   <dateline>17 de marzo de 1942</dateline>
   
   <salute>Queridos papás,</salute>
  </opener>
  
  <p>Recibí su tarjeta y hoy recibí su carta. Me alegró recibir noticias suyas.</p>
  
  <p>Acabo de escribirle a esos señores para decirles que ya había aceptado un trabajo de oficina.</p>
  
  <p>Jim estuvo aquí esta noche y fuimos al pueblo por un rato. Acabo de regresar y ya escribí esas otras cartas, así que les escribo para alcanzar a ponerlas en el correo esta misma noche. Las envío desde la <app loc="1"><rdg>estación</rdg></app><app loc="2"><rdg>depósito</rdg></app>.</p>
  
  <p>El Sr. Lollis se fue a Chicago hoy en la noche y regresa el jueves en la mañana.</p>
  
  <p>El sábado pasado Sr. Lollis y yo fuimos a Omaha. Vio a algunas personas en la tarde, luego cenamos ‘un pollo salvaje’ (medio pollo), y después de eso fuimos al cine y vimos tres películas y estaba ahí la escuela de KMA. Quizá hayan escuchado el programa de KMA, porque lo transmitieron. El Sr. Mr. pagó la cena y las películas. Cuando íbamos a volver a casa el clima se puso muy mal , así que nos alquiló una habitación
   
   <pb facs="shan_l.463.jpg"/>
   
   en las cabañas Tourist Tower, así que nos quedamos hasta el domingo en la mañana y luego regresamos. Me dejó conducir camino a Omaha y también allá.</p>
  
  <p>Estoy bien. Creo que este trabajo tiene futuro. Ahora estamos limpiando y preparando todo antes de que se vaya el campamento. La próxima semana llegan nuestras provisiones y suministros. ¡Caramba! Deberían ver la orden que hicimos anoche —4000 libras de azúcar —300 libras de azúcar para repostería —300libras de pasas, y grandes cantidades de todo. Les contaré todo sobre el campamento cuando vuelva a casa, solo que no sé cuándo será.</p>
  
  <p>Debo ayudar con las provisiones y suministros —mantengo y escribo informes — y ayudo en el economato (es el lugar donde vendemos todo lo que puede ofrecérsele a alguien que trabaje aquí —ropa-dulces, etc).</p>
  
  <p>Anoche trabajamos hasta 11:30—pero no fue muy pesado.</p>
  
  <p>Es que estoy trabajando en el ferrocarril C.B. &amp; Q pero para la compañía John J. Grier, que tiene estos campamentos. Nosotros   alojamos y les damos de comer a los trabadores del C.B. &amp; Q. por $8.75 a la semana.</p>
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.464.jpg"/>
  
  <p>Ahora somos solamente cinco, pero va a haber más de 200 <add resp="iv001">hombres</add> el 6 de abril que abra el campamento. Vamos a estar en Crete casi una semana y después nos vamos a St. Joe y después a Colorado, luego a Wisconsin y no sé a dónde más después de eso, porque nosotros trabajamos en todas las líneas del C.B. &amp; Q.</p>
  
  <p>Creo que les conté que me dijo que a veces podía conducir su carro. Es un Studebaker Commander 1941. [El Sr. Lollis?] lo tiene asegurado por $50,000, y va a poner mi nombre en póliza junto con el suyo.</p>
  
  <p>Me dejan usar una máquina de escribir portátil marca Royal.</p>
  
  <p>Es posible que Jim y yo vayamos a casa alguna noche o algún domingo. Estoy planeando ir con Jim a la obra ‘Jr. Play’ esa misma noche.</p>

  <p>De veras que nos dan de comer muy bien. El Sr. Lollis va al pueblo y compra todo de lo mejor. Nos sirven carne en cada comida, papas, pan, mantequilla, y casi siempre una o dos verduras para acompañar. Compra bollos, pasteles, etc.</p>
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.465.jpg"/>
  
  <p>Creo que terminaré por esta noche y me iré a enviar esta carta. La <app loc="1"><rdg>estación</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>depósito</rdg></app> está a solo una cuadra.</p>
  
  <closer>
   <salute>Salúdenme a todos. Su hijo y hermano,</salute>                    
   <signed>William F. Schubert</signed>
  </closer>
  
  <postscript>
   <p>P.D. Tenemos nuestra propia planta de luz de 110 voltios, un vagón para la cocina, vagones comedor, vagones litera y todo, incluyendo regaderas.</p>
   <p>Recibí una carta del Servicio Civil. Saqué un promedio de 93.67, pero creo que me voy a quedar con este trabajo incluso si dentro de poco me dan mi cambio al S.C.</p>
  </postscript>     
  
 </div1>
</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>