<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://jetson.unl.edu/cdrh/schemas/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L074.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Lillian Wilhelm to Mr. and Mrs. Wm. Schubert and Family, January 30, 1958</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Lillian Wilhelm a Sr. y Sra. Wm. Schubert y Familia, 30 de enero, 1958</title>
<author>Lillian Wilhelm</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="iv002">Velázquez, Isabel</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L074.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Lillian Wilhelm</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Lillian Wilhelm to Mr. and Mrs. Wm. Schubert and Family</title>
<date when="1958-01-30">January 01, 1958</date>
<extent>4 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="lw001" medium="pencil"><p>Media: lead/graphite</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<person role="sender" xml:id="lw001">
<persName>Lillian Wilhelm</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient" xml:id="sbs001">
<persName>Mrs. Wm. Schubert</persName> <!--Is Mrs. Wm. Schubert also Sandra Baros Schubert?-->
</person>
<person role="recipient" xml:id="wfs002">
<persName>Mr. Wm. Schubert</persName>
</person>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#iv002">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.220.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<note>tell John, Given's Jack, marjie's "hello" for us - hope they are staying free of colds, flu.</note>
<dateline>Jan 28 '58</dateline>
<add>Tues Eve.</add>

<address><addrLine>Dear Bill Sandra, family</addrLine></address>

<salute>Happy New Year 'to one, all, we surely hope it brings you, yours lots of Health Happiness, Prosperity</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>Glad to get your xmas card, good letter. So sorry to hear you had been in the hospital Bill –with the flu, heart trouble. Encouraging to hear you were able to be up, at work again but do try, take it easier. Can’t help but feel that if you do, no with the different treatments, medicine they have for all sorts of illness you will be alright mind the doctor surely mabe a good boss don’t?<unclear reason="illegible">¿</unclear> Hope the rest of the family are fine.</p>

<p>Know you had a nice xmas going to John, Given’s – wish we could have <unclear reason="illegible">pulsed</unclear> in on you all. We had a good xmas –the clan came over as planned for dinner <unclear reason="illegible"/> Sun before xmas, Santy was god to all.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.222.jpg"/>

<p>2/</p>

<p>Nice to hear that Billy was given the award last year for being top one in his grade! That is quite an honor. Good Bobby doesn’t have far to go to school. Expect Pamela will like school real well. You folks are putting forth a lot of effort to improve your house. With the room for the boys in the basement, also wanting to make a “rec” room down there, too. Just don’t try to do it all overnite. <unclear reason="illegible"/> Fine Billy is on Cub Scouts, that Sandra will be Den Mother. Del is in Cub Scouts, gets lots of good out of it He had his birthday yesterday Jan. 27, his folks between all of them. Mande Shirley, Patty, her hubby, gave him a bi cycle so he was one tickled boy. We gave him a package of different kinds of candy bars.</p>

<p>Excuse the scribbling folks, am sort of sleepy headed. Have been trying to catch up a little on our letter writing –don’t pretend to keep it up to date anymore – just hack away at it now & then! With so many relatives</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.224.jpg"/>

<p>3/</p>

<p>one of his favorite <unclear reason="illegible">jr</unclear> programs, Bruce is writing <unclear reason="illegible">Lou</unclear>. He took <unclear reason="illegible">Lou</unclear> backs up to Flagstaff yesterday for second semester college. She had registered last week already for the second semester. B. registered today for his second semester. The Triple C’s. the older youth group in our church went up to our Church camp on Mingus mountain  up north west about 100 mi this last week end for what was to be their annual snow party. Well, they didn’t find enough snow for a proper snow man! Let alone enough to sleigh ride on! They had a lot of fun. Mostly eating, hiking around on the mountain. The higher colder altitude really gave them the big appetites. The camp is at about 1 ½ mi. elevation. It’s a nice camp is really made use of in the summer time The Triple c’s were snowed in up there for a short while last year!</p>

<p>Excuse my pencil, paper too folks. B. is using my good pen, I’m always buying some pretty stationery so I’ll have pretty</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.226.jpg"/>

<p>4/</p>

<p>paper to write my letters on but always give it away as gifts.</p>

<p>We had a nice day here – not windy for a change. Have had an unusual amount of wind this month. Had a little rain Sun eve. enough to settle some of the dust anyway. Had a letter from Lillie Minick in Syracuse yesterday, she was telling that they had some snow there last week for a change.</p>

<p>My sweet peas are staring to bloom. Have some bedding plants started to put in the two front yard tree wells –will wait a while to set them out as we get an <unclear reason="illegible">unseasonal</unclear> frost of an early morning. Have Pansies. Sweet Alyssum, stocks to set in the tree wells. The boys plan to paint the house in about a week, the paint that’s on it is starting to flake off pretty bad so they that if they got one good coat of primer, one of top paint, it would last then about five years. Will close for now, write when you can. Always happy to hear from you.</p>

<closer>  
<salute>Love</salute>                  
<signed>Lillian & family</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>
</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
