<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L021.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from José Jesús Samaniego to Jesusita Baros Torres, October 15, 1938</title>
<title type="main">Carta de José Jesús Samaniego a Jesusita Baros Torres, 15 de octubre, 1938</title>
<author>Samaniego, José Jesús</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="iv002">Velázquez, Isabel</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L021.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Samaniego, José Jesús</author>
<title level="m" type="main">José Jesús Samaniego to Jesusita Baros Torres</title>
<date when="1938-10-15">October 15, 1938</date>
<extent>4 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="js001" medium="pencil"><p>Media: lead/graphite</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="js001">Samaniego, José Jesús</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1938-10-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#iv002">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.090.jpg"/>
                  
<opener>
<address><addrLine>1 Juchipila Zacal</addrLine></address>
<dateline>Otubre 15 de 1938</dateline>
<salute>Señora eliboria flemate</salute>
</opener>

<p>mi mui atenta y cariñosa mama yo me a le grare que alresibo de estos tres 3 rin glones se in cuentren sino bedad que la que de mi se des pide es buena grasias a dios</p>

<p>pues mama des pues de saludarlos conel cariño de siempre ledigo losigete pues antes de platicarle al guna cosas que me pasanprimero le doi los sentimientos porque nomea esqürito quizás en nal guna cosa la ofendí pero siasies perdóname mamita no lo ise adrede pongatension alo que mepasa mama no se inmajina enla confusión que llo me encuentro le boi a</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.091.jpg"/>

<fw>2</fw>
<p>platicar como y de que manera me encuentro ma de berguensa desirle qüiero que e aga favor de prestarme 15 pesos oro para yrme de juchipila me atitulan que llo estaba ena morando una mujer casada noes sierto pero tanto y tanto senpeso a de sir asta que llego a oídos del marido y <unclear reason="illegible">en</unclear> mediantemente casila mato a leñasos ydiai seria como al <unclear reason="illegible">peso</unclear> de media noche lle garon el marido de la señora y un ermano queriendo me disque me matar no me mataron porque no qüisieron llo que iba aser para dos pero se que dice que como dios lede lisensia no mes capo no quiere a</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.091.jpg"/>

<fw>3</fw>
<p>mas que lo grar una upurtunidad de in contrarme solo en nun lugar donde naiden sedecuenta a si me platico un amigo que el tiene de sus confiansas p ues mama llo no lo qureo pero nilo dudo tanpoco considerando que son unos <unclear reason="illegible">casos</unclear> de desgreñarse u no ya de mas de eso medisen que meretire de mi pueblo que para que mañana o cuando meballa aen <unclear reason="illegible">felisar</unclear> conel oel con migo mama viendo llo esto algo de motivo que <unclear reason="illegible">di</unclear> y llo que tengo ganas de salir <unclear reason="illegible">me</unclear> llo mama mi salida es para ca con Ud Sea que pueda permanecer aqüi con ustedes o sea que me echen para fuera</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.092.jpg"/>

<fw>4</fw>

<p>Porque se que esta mui trabajoso para <unclear reason="illegible">llo</unclear> mi gusto es mama de conocerlos aus tede yustedes que me conoscanami sea que dure undia sea que dure 2 lo mis mo quelle gare en nun mes o llegare en dos no se la suerte que me toque lo que si le digo mama que no me deje de la mano qüiero que me aga ese favor conlo que pueda y en lo que pueda si enesta vida no le pago abersi en lotra mi <unclear reason="illegible">dilasion</unclear> de salir es que me conteste Ud</p>
                
<closer>Saludes para chui y santitos re siba saludes demi esposa para todos mes quri con la direision esta calle rosales numero 63 es cuanto
<signed>Jesus Samaniego</signed>
</closer>
               
</div1>


<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.090.jpg"/>
                  
<opener>
<address><addrLine>1 Juchipila Zacatecas</addrLine></address>
<dateline>October 15 1938</dateline>
<salute>Mrs. Eliboria Flemate</salute>
</opener>

<p>my very gracious and loving mother, mom I will be happy if these three <add resp="iv001">few</add> lines find you without news <app loc="1"><rdg>well</rdg></app>, this <add resp="iv001">letter</add> leaves me well, thank God.</p>

<p>Well mother, after greeting you with the same love as always I tell you the following, but before telling you about what is happening to me, I’ll tell you that I’m sad because you haven’t written to me. I may have offended you in some way. If this is the case, please forgive me <term type="diminutive">mom</term> <app loc="1"><rdg>mommy</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>mother</rdg></app>, because it wasn’t on purpose. <add resp="iv001">Now</add> pay attention to what is happening to me mom, you can’t imagine the confusion in which I find myself. I’m going to</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.091.jpg"/>

<fw>2</fw>
<p>tell you how and in which manner I find myself. I feel ashamed <app loc="1"><rdg>embarrassed</rdg></app> to ask you to do me the favor of lending me 15 pesos to leave Juchipila. They accuse me of courting a married woman. It’s not true, but it’s been repeated so much that word got to the husband and he almost killed her <add resp="iv001">by hitting her</add> with a log. And from there, the husband and one brother of his arrived around midnight saying they wanted to kill me. They didn’t kill me because they didn’t want to, because what could I do against two? But it’s being said that he is saying that if God allows it I will not escape. He wants no more</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.091.jpg"/>

<fw>3</fw>
<p>than to get the opportunity to find me alone in a place where no one finds out, this is what a trusted friend of his told me. Well, mom, I don’t believe it, but I don’t doubt it either, considering the cases <app loc="1"><rdg>that these are the type of cases</rdg></app><certainty locus="name" cert="medium"/> <add resp="iv001">sometimes</add> involve pulling someone’s hair <app loc="1"><rdg>fighting</rdg></app>. I’m told to leave my town so that I don’t get into a fight with him or he with me <certainty locus="name" cert="medium"/>. Mom, seeing all this I <add resp="iv001">may have</add> given him some motive <app loc="1" cert="low"><rdg>Gives me motive to leave</rdg></app> And I want to leave. My departure is towards here <app loc="1"><rdg>to be here</rdg></app>with you <add resp="iv001">here in Colorado, with you</add>. Whether I can remain here with <term type="plural">you</term>, or whether I’m returned <app loc="1" cert="medium"><rdg>deported</rdg></app></p>

<pb facs="shan_l.092.jpg"/>

<fw>4</fw>

<p>Because I know it’s very difficult for me. My desire <app loc="1"><rdg>my wish</rdg></app> is to get to know <term type="plural">you</term>, and for <term type="plural">you</term> to get to know me. Whether it lasts a day or two, and whether it takes me a month or two to arrive, depending on my luck. What I do ask of you, mom, is not to abandon me. <add resp="iv001">I ask you to</add> help me with what you can and in any way you can, and if I cannot repay you in this lifetime, maybe I will be able to in the next. The delay in my departure is <add resp="iv001">I'm waiting for</add> your response.</p>
                
<closer>Give my regards to Chuy <add resp="iv001">Jesus</add> and <term type="diminutive">Santitos</term> <add resp="iv001">Baby Santos</add>. Receive regards from my wife for everybody.
<add resp="iv001">Please</add>write to me at this address: Rosales street 63. This is all that 

<signed>Jesus Samaniego</signed>
</closer>

</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.088.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>after 10 days Return to</addrLine>
<addrLine>Demetrio Flemate</addrLine>
<addrLine>Juchipila Zacatecas</addrLine>
<addrLine>mexico</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Jesusita Baros</addrLine>
<addrLine>in care of Bill Kennedy</addrLine>
<addrLine>Route #3 Longmont Colorado</addrLine>
<addrLine>U.S.</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<pb facs="shan_l.089.jpg"/>

<ab type="postmark">
AGUASCALIENTES<lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible"/><lb/>
AGS<lb/>
</ab>

</div1>



</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>