<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L078.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert, February 4, 1957</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Jesusita Baros Torres a Santos Baros Schubert, 4 de febrero, 1957</title>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Mendell, Kate</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L078.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1957-02-04">February 2, 1957</date>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jbt001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1957-02-04"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#km">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.240.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<fw>1</fw>
<address><addrLine>ft. Lupton Colo</addrLine></address>
<dateline>4, Febrero, 1957.</dateline>

<salute>Querida hija,</salute>
</opener>

<p>la precente es para saludarlos á todos tanto á ti, como al Bill, á los niños;</p>
                
<p>ya ase dias que reciví esta; yo estaba con pena de Uds; y te escriví y ese dia que fui á echar la <del>cata</del> carta; ese mismo dia aye esta; onde benía los retratos de los niños muchas gracias sabieron muy bien yo quisiera tener un retrato de todos de tí, el Bill; y los niños;</p>

<p>me escribío la Betty, y recibí mucho gusto; tan siquiera si acuerda, de mí yo pensaba que no podía escribir en español pero sí sabe;</p>

<p>que bueno, dice que esta trabajando ella y su esposo; y la suegra le cuída los niños;</p>

<p>y tiene muchas ganas de berme;</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.241.jpg"/>
<fw>2</fw>

<p>ojala y biniera algún día; yo le agredesco mucho; yo ya tan vieja; y sin poder ablar el ingles, pienso que asta se afrentaran, que diran; esta viejá; tonta ní save ablar, nada;</p>

<p>pues yo sí quiero, ablar el ingles. pero no puedo; asta á mí me da pena; bueno Helen es muy buena con migo; ella me á llebado al Doctor; y tambien aversí areģlamos el seguro socíal; aquí biene una bes al mes; quíen sabe quedaron de escribir; bueno y dime como an seguido el Bill, con su enfer-meda; yo parese que estoy muy bien no te tardes mucho en escríbirme porque yo tengo pena de ti;</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.242.jpg"/>

<fw>3.</fw>

<p>muchos recuerdos para ti y el Bill y los niños; de jessee y familia; y Max y de mí tu mamá que te deseo, que estes bien vivan agusto, en tu casa, y con tu esposo. aqui cada rato se miran pleitos con los maridos les pegan; y ay ando yo metiendo paz; que feo, que triste; y luego me acuerdo, de Uds; tu nunca me dises nada; ojala y esten bien; es lo que siempre le pido á Dios que ayude tanto <add>á ti</add> con tu esposo, y hijos;</p>

<closer> 
<salute>tu mamá</salute>    
               
<signed>jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.240.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<fw>1</fw>
<address><addrLine>ft. Lupton Colo</addrLine></address>
<dateline>February 4, 1957.</dateline>

<salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
</opener>

<p>this letter is to greet you all: You, Bill and the kids.</p>
                
<p>I got your letter several days ago. I was worried about you, so I wrote you, and the day I went to mail the letter, that same day, I found this <add resp="iv001">letter</add> with the photos of the kids. Thank you, they came out very well. I would like to have a photo of all of you: You, Bill and the kids.</p>

<p>Betty wrote to me and it made me very happy. At least she remembers me. I thought she couldn’t write in Spanish, but she does know how.</p>

<p>That’s good. She says that she they are working, her husband and her, and her mother-in-law takes care of the kids;</p>

<p>and she is very eager to see me.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.241.jpg"/>
<fw>2</fw>

<p>I wish she would come one day. I appreciate her so. I’m so old and can’t speak English. I think they may even be offended, they may say ‘this foolish old woman doesn’t even know how to speak or anything’.</p>

<p>Well, I do want to speak English, but I can’t. Even I get embarrassed. Well, Helen is very good to me; she has taken me to the doctor, and also, to see if they give me the Social Security. It comes once a month here. Who knows, they promised to write. Well, tell me how is Bill with his illness. I seem to be very well. Don’t take too long to write to me because I worry about you.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.242.jpg"/>

<fw>3.</fw>

<p>many regards <app loc="1"><rdg>warm regards</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>much love</rdg></app> to you and to Bill and the kids from Jesse and family; and from Max and from me, your mother who wishes that you are well, and living comfortably <app loc="1"><rdg>happily</rdg></app> in your home and with your husband. Around here we see fights very often; the husbands hit them, and there I go trying to appease things. How ugly, how sad. And later I think about you. You never tell me anything; I hope you are well. It’s what I always ask from God, that he help you with your husband and your kids.</p>

<closer> 
<salute>Your mom</salute>    
               
<signed>Jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>