<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L155.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Jess Baros to Santos Baros Schubert, January 2, 1976</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Jess Baros a Santos Baros Schubert, 02 de enero, 1976</title>
<author>Baros, Jess</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L155.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros, Jess</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jess Baros to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1976-01-02">January 2, 1976</date>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jjb001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<particDesc>
<person role="sender" xml:id="jbt001">
<persName>Jesusita B Torres</persName>
</person>
<person role="recipient" xml:id="sbs001">
<persName>W. F. Schubert</persName>
</person>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#af">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.562.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>Jan 2, 1976</dateline>
<address><addrLine>Ft Lupton Colo</addrLine></address>

<salute>Dear Sandra&amp;Bill</salute>
</opener>

<p>hoping This letter finds you&amp;your family in good health.</p>
                
<p>We are all fine, thanks be to God.</p>

<p>First, I’m returning the $10.00 sent to me to send to mother’s relatives in Mexico. I think me, you&amp;I, should forget about the past and not start something that we would not want to continue, I’m referring to the sending of donations&amp;other requests that they might ask of because of mother&amp;so forth, their relation to her&amp;thus to us also.</p>

<p>about max, Well, don’t you worry about max’s welfare he’s doing fine, he gets between old age pension&amp;R.R. retirement about $200.00 per month. Plus the rents of the houses in back of $160.00 per month. this expenses are the cost of the <del/> utilities plus $30.00 per week to Gloría Botello. which takes very good care of him&amp;the house. the house is spotless.</p>

<p>The arrangement made with that family is that Mrs. Botello take care of max, and that they would buy&amp;pay for the food for all of them, but that they could live in the house, not pay rent or for utilities or telephone, local calls. and she would get $30.00 a week. of course, I’ve been giving her a few dollars on the side to keep her interested in staying, because she is very good to him.</p>

<p>I don’t know how long they will stay.

<pb facs="shan_l.564.jpg"/>

<fw>2</fw>

I hope its at least until Max has no need for them. But we’ll see, Mr Botello is working in the Kitayama flower nursery.</p>

<p>yes, Mrs Baca&amp;Fred were over to see us this last summer, it was really a surprised. they really came out to see some people in Golden and were passing thro to Albuquerque, they stayed about 3 – 4 hours, they went on to Albuquerque.</p>

<p>Mrs Baca first went to max’s house and ask if this was the house where max Torres lived, the lady said yes and were invited in max asked them who she was, when she told him she was mrs Felipita Baca, <del/> he tried to stand up to greet her and almost fell, but Fred caught him.</p>

<p>I never knew how much max loved mother and how much he still thinks about her, even now, when we sometimes talk about mother, he starts to cry. One never knows. They use to fight&amp;argue sometimes, something terrible, but underneath was a great love for each others.</p>

<p>the night before mother died, we had a talk about max, she told me if she ever passed away before max. to take care of him. she was concerned that maybe I would forget about him, being that he was not our real father.</p>

<p>I assured her not to worry, that max would be alright.

<pb facs="shan_l.566.jpg"/>

<fw>3</fw>

And he is alright but sometimes I really get mad at him for some of the things he does, but then I have to remind myself that he is a frighten old, crippled man that does not understand that some of the things I do is really for his benefit.</p>

<p>Well, I didn’t intended to write all these things in my letter to you, but I think I tried to explain to you, that max is <del/> <add>fine</add>, is taken care of, and not to worry, now my concern is, take care of yourself, your back&amp;eyesight.</p>

<p>Do not over exert yourself&amp;have regular check ups in the eyes. O.K.?</p>

<p>had a nice Xmas, spent Xmas Eve with Jerry&amp;Laura. xmas day had dinner up mary’s house, new years eve&amp;day stayed home and watched the foot ball games.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Love to you all</salute>                    
<signed>Jess&amp;Helen&amp;Mark</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>
</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>