<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L161.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Santos Baros Schubert to William F. Schubert, October 7, 1950</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Santos Baros Schubert to William F. Schubert, 07 de octubre, 1950</title>
<author>Baros Schubert, Santos</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Mendell, Kate</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
 <name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L161.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Schubert, Santos</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Santos Baros Schubert to William F. Schubert</title>
<date when="1950-10-07">October 7, 1950</date>
<extent>4 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>4 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>4 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="sbs001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1950-10-07"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1950-10-10"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#km">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.594.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>Oct 7, 1950</dateline>

<salute>Dearest Bill,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>Have received all your letters and we’re very glad to hear from “Daddy”.</p>

<p>So sorry that I don’t write every day but that don’t mean that I don’t love you or miss you. Billy misses you, too and every night he wants his Daddy&amp;go to his trailer home.</p>

<p>Helen&amp;Jess took me to the Spanish show last night. Mother’s leg didn’t feel so good so she stayed home and I left Billy home. </p>

<p>Bet you think that I’m having a good time – well I’m not having a bad time either. Can’t get around much like when you came with me last year. I have only

<pb facs="shan_l.595.jpg"/>

gone to Denver once Wed.&amp;stayed there with Jerry Wed. nite and came home Thurs. 5:P.M.</p>

<p>I went shopping for mother. Bought her a house dress&amp;hand vacuum cleaner like ours for only $20.86. Then I went to get my reservation for Oct. 22nd Sun at 4:PM. In the Denver Zephyr. If you want me to come home sooner why then you let me know, so I can cancel reservation.</p> 

<p>Wed. night while we’re in Denver Jerry&amp;Johnnie took us to see your aunts. Stayed for about 2 hrs.&amp;then Jerry&amp;Johnnie came after us. And I had a heck of a night. Billy cried, couldn’t sleep. Kids down the basement cried, too. I didn’t sleep at all. They wanted to bring us home but I was so tired. Took the bus 5:PM.</p>

<p>I won’t go to Denver anymore unless Jess could take me&amp;then I’d like to take Billy to the City Park as they have a baby elephant. And I haven’t vested those ladies where I sued to work with.</p>

<p>Jerry came to play with Billy this afternoon but Billy is still asleep. He had a nice bath.</p>

<p>Yesterday was really windy&amp;today so nice&amp;warm. It hasn’t rained here at all. Mother says it hasn’t rained all summer.</p>  

<p>Helen isn’t working anymore as there were two nights that froze everything so Cathy isn’t here anymore. Billy misses her, too. Helen received a good check $120.00 for only two wks. She’s going to buy a gas heater. They’re going to have gas in their house.</p>

<p>I better write to marjorie&amp;thank her for Billy’s sweater. I’ll write

<pb facs="shan_l.596.jpg"/>

again some other day. So don’t worry about us. We’re fine.</p>

<p>Billy just woke up.</p>

<p>Did Betty send anything for Billy’s birthday?</p>

<p>Glad to hear you finally have the new trailer at your home.</p> 

<p>Billy sends you all his love&amp;kisses.</p>

<closer>
<salute>All my Love,</salute>                    
<signed>Sandra</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>I love you.<lb/>
I miss you.<lb/></p>
 <label>P.S.</label><lb/><p>
Don’t forget when we’re coming home Oct 22nd in the Denver Zephyr<lb/></p>
</postscript>
 
</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.592.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Sandra Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>P.O. Box 681</addrLine>
<addrLine>Ft. Lupton, Colo</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mr. W. F. Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>Camp 67</addrLine>
<addrLine>Rulo, Nebr.</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
FORT LUPTON<lb/> 
OCT 9<lb/>
8 AM<lb/>
1950<lb/>
COLO<lb/>
</ab>

<figure type="stamp">
<p></p>
</figure>

<pb facs="shan_l.593.jpg"/>

<ab type="postmark">
RULO<lb/>
OCT 10<lb/>
1950<lb/>
NEBR.<lb/>
</ab>

</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
  
<pb facs="shan_l.594.jpg"/>
  
<opener>
<dateline>7 de octubre de 1950</dateline>
<salute>Querido Bill:</salute>
</opener>

<p>Recibimos todas tus cartas y nos dio mucho gusto recibir noticias de ‘papi’.</p>

<p>Disculpa que no te escriba todos los días, pero no quiere decir que no te ame o que no te extrañe. Billy te extraña también y todas las noches quiere a su papi y quiere irse a su casa tráiler.</p>

<p>Anoche Helen y Jess me llevaron a ver una película en español. A mi mamá le dolía la pierna, así que se quedó en casa y dejé a Billy en casa.</p>

<p>Apuesto a que crees que me estoy divirtiendo mucho. Bueno, pues no me la estoy pasando tan mal, tampoco. No puedo salir mucho, como cuando viniste conmigo el año pasado. Solo he

<pb facs="shan_l.595.jpg"/>
 
ido a Denver una vez, el miércoles, y me quedé allá con Terry el miércoles en la noche y volví a la casa el jueves a las 5:00 pm.</p>

<p>Fui de compras con mi mamá. Le compré un vestido de andar por casa y una aspiradora de mano como la nuestra por solo $20.86. Luego fui a hacer mi reservación para el 22 de octubre en el Zephyr de Denver. Si quieres que regrese antes avísame, para cancelar la reservación.</p>

<p>El miércoles en la noche, que  estuvimos en Denver Terry y Johnnie nos llevaron a ver a tus tías. Nos quedamos unas dos horas y luego Terry y Johnnie volvieron a recogernos. Pasé muy mala noche. Billy estaba llorando y no podía dormir. Los niños estaban en el sótano y lloraron mucho. Yo no dormí nada. Querían traernos a casa, pero yo estaba muy cansada. Tomé el autobús de las 5:00 pm.</p>

<p>No voy a volver a ir a Denver a menos que Jess me pueda llevar. Si es así me gustaría llevar a Billy al parque de la ciudad porque tienen un elefantito. Y no he visitado a las señoras aquellas con las que trabajé.</p>
 
<p>Jerry vino a jugar con Billy hoy en la tarde pero Billy sigue dormido. Tomó un buen baño. </p> 

<p>Anoche hizo mucho viento y hoy está muy bonito y templado. No ha llovido nada. Mamá dice que no llovió en todo el verano.</p>

<p>Helen ya no está trabajando porque hubo dos semanas en las que se congeló todo, así que Cathy ya no está aquí. Bily la extraña muchísimo. A Helen le dieron un buen cheque, $120.00 por solo dos semanas. Va a comprar un calentón de gas. Van a tener gas en su casa.</p>

<p>Más vale que le escriba a Marjorie para darle las gracias por el suéter de Billy. Volveré a escribirte 
 
<pb facs="shan_l.596.jpg"/> 

de nuevo otro día. No te preocupes por nosotros, que estamos bien.</p>
 
<p>Billy acaba de despertar.</p>

<p>¿Betty mandó algo para el cumpleaños de Billy? </p> 

<p>Me alegró saber que ya tienes el tráiler nuevo como tu casa.</p>

<p>Billy te manda todo su amor y muchos besos.</p>
 
 <closer>
  <salute>Con todo mi amor, </salute>                    
  <signed>Sandra</signed>
 </closer>
 
 <postscript>
  <p>Te amo.<lb/>
   Te extraño.<lb/></p>
  <label>P.D.</label><lb/><p>
   No se te olvide qué día regresamos. 22 de octubre, en el Zephyr de Denver.<lb/></p>
 </postscript>
 
</div1> 

</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>