<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L197.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert, April 30, 1958</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Jesusita Baros Torres a Santos Baros Schubert, 30 de abril, 1958</title>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Reyes, Sara</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
 <name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L197.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Torres,Jesusita</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1958-04-30">April 30, 1958</date>
<extent>3 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jbt001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1958-04-30"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1958-04-30"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#sr">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.693.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>ft, Lupton Colo</addrLine></address>
<dateline>april 30,-1958</dateline>

<salute>Querida hija,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>la precente es para Saludarte síempre deceando que esten bíen todos asi como nosotros estamos es por lo que le doy Gracías á Díos,</p>

<p>pues bíen, recíví tu carta, yo siempre con la pena de Uds; le díje á jess que les hablara por . Telepon; vino me llevo, para su casa y le abla al Bill;</p>

<p>si estaba poco malo de una mano, ya asía como 2, meses que se abía cortado un dedo muy malamente; se corto los nervíos de los dedos de la mano hisquerda en el trabajo; y el Doctor le cosío la cortado pero le cosío los nervios, de modo que no

<pb facs="shan_l.694.jpg"/>

los podía mober; y ya que se alíbío pero no tenía movimien<add>to</add> en sus dos dedos los mas grandes de la mano hisquerda, no podía trabajar, y le bolviern á ser operacíon; entonses se fue al Hospital por unos 10, días y le bolvieron aser operacíon para soltarle los nervios que le abían cosído y entonses le pusíeron una mano de llezo asta la canilla y unos fierros en los dedos; pero haora en esta semana se los quita<add>ron</add> y todabía no trabaja; la Helen sí, ya esta trabajando y el esta en la casa; max trabajo como un dia de cada semana, porque esta muy llovido; mucha agua;</p>

<p>pues pobre del Bill ya se le acabaron las dos tias que tenía en Denver

<pb facs="shan_l.695.jpg"/>

ya mero acaban el cuarto que te platíque todabía no vienen las puertas; pero yo píenzo que cuando tu bengas ya estara acabado y siga bíen el Bill que no se enferme,</p>

<p>que bonito, salío el Billy boy en el retrato y el Babe no se á retratado mandame uno tambíen, para tener recuerdos de cuando estaban en la escuela;</p>

<p>bueno híja es todo muchos recuerdos del jess y famílía y de Max y de tu mama que mejor deseo berlos que escríbirles ojala y bengan pronto</p> 

<closer>
<salute>tu mamá</salute>                    
<signed>jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>


<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.693.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Ft. Lupton, Colorado</addrLine></address>
<dateline>April 30, - 1958</dateline>

<salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>This letter is to greet you, wishing as always that you are all well, as are we, for which I thank God.</p>

<p>Well, I received you letter. I’m always worried for you all. I told Jess to call you on the telephone. He came and took me to his house and he called Bill.</p>

<p>Yes, his hand was a bit bad. He had cut one of his fingers very badly. He cut the nerves of the fingers in his left hand at work, and the doctor stitched the wound, but he sewed the nerves, so <add resp="iv001">he</add> could not

<pb facs="shan_l.694.jpg"/>

move them <app loc="1"><rdg>the fingers</rdg></app>. And he healed, but he could not move the two biggest fingers on his left hand. He couldn’t work and they operated on him again, so he went to the hospital for about ten days, and they operated on him to release the nerves that they had stitched together and they put a cast in his hand, up to the forearm, and some metal things in his fingers, but they removed them this week and he still cannot work. Helen yes, she is working, and he is at home. Max worked about a day a week because it’s been very rainy, lots of water.</p>

<p>Well, poor Bill, he lost the aunts that he had in Denver.

<pb facs="shan_l.695.jpg"/>

The room I was telling you about is almost done. The doors haven’t come yet, but I think that when you come it will be finished. And <add resp="iv001">I hope</add> that Bill continues to be well and that he doesn’t get sick.</p>

<p>Billy Boy came out very handsome in the portrait. And Babe, hasn’t he been photographed? Send me one <add resp="iv001">photo of babe</add> too, to have memories <app loc="1" cert="high"><rdg>mementos</rdg></app> of when they were in school.</p>

<p>Well daughter, this is all. Many regards <app loc="1"><rdg>much love</rdg></app> from Jess and his family, and from Max and your mom, who would rather see you than write to you. I hope that you come soon.</p> 

<closer>
<salute>Your mom</salute>                    
<signed>Jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>


<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.691.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>P.O. Box 681</addrLine>
<addrLine>Ft. Lupton Colo</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>mrs. W F. Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>1016 South 40th st;</addrLine> 
<addrLine>Lincoln 10 nebraska</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
FORT LUPTON<lb/>
APR 30<lb/> 
5 30PM<lb/> 
1958<lb/>
COLO.<lb/>
</ab>

<figure type="stamp">
<p></p>
</figure>

</div1>
 
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
  
<pb facs="shan_l.693.jpg"/>
  
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Fort Lupton, Colorado</addrLine></address>
<dateline>April 30,1958</dateline>
   
<salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
</opener>

<p>this letter is to greet you, wishing as always that you are all well, as are we, for which I thank God.</p>

<p>Well, I received you letter. I’m always worried for you all. I told Jess to call you on the telephone. He came and took me to his house and he called Bill.</p>
 
<p>Yes, his hand was a bit bad. He had cut one of his fingers very badly. He cut the nerves of the fingers in his left hand at work, and the doctor stitched the wound, but he sewed the nerves, so he could not
 
<pb facs="shan_l.694.jpg"/> 

move them. And he healed, but he could not move the two biggest fingers on his left hand. He couldn’t work and they operated on him again, so he went to the hospital for about ten days, and they operated on him to release the nerves that they had stitched together and they put a cast in his hand, up to the forearm, and some metal things in his fingers, but they removed them this week and he still cannot work. Helen yes, she is working, and he is at home. Max worked about a day a week because it’s been very rainy, lots of water.</p>

<p>Well, poor Bi, he lost the aunts that he had in Denver.

<pb facs="shan_l.695.jpg"/>

The room I was telling you about is almost done. The doors haven’t come yet, but I think that when you come it will be finished. And I hope that Bill continues to be well and that he doesn’t get sick.</p>

<p>Billy Boy came out very handsome in the portrait. And Babe, hasn’t he been photographed? Send me one <add cert="high" resp="ji">photo of babe</add> too, to have memories of when they were in school.</p>
 
<p>Well daughter, this is all. Many regards from Jess and his family, and from Max and your mom, who would rather see you than write to you. I hope that you come soon.</p>
 
<closer>
<salute>Your mom</salute>                    
<signed>Jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>
 
</div1> 

</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>