<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L077.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de Jesusita Baros Torres a Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Mendell, Kate</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L077.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note>Date is unknown as it was not listed</note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jbt001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p/></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#km">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.236.jpg"/>
                
<opener>

<address><addrLine>ft, Lupton colo</addrLine></address>
<fw>1</fw>

<salute>Querida hija</salute>
</opener>

<p>la presente es para saludarte tanto á ti como á tu espezo, y los niños; recivi tu <del>carta</del> Grandmother Card que me mando Billy boy; ojala y esten buenos aliviados,</p>
                
<p>pues que ya estan trabajando aquí Max; y siempre se entretiene un en el trabajo de la casa;</p>

<p> pero me dijo Helen que tenia mucho gusto, porque iba á tener una nueba hayjada, y la Kathy dise es una siter; pues que bueno; á ella le gustan mucho los babys parese; y tambíen me dijo que ban á benir para aca ft, Lupton;</p>

<p>pues ya haora se; para no rentar los cuartos; saves que me dilate poquito en no contestarte, porque estube muy mala; si deveras que estube mala; pues sabes que todos los días devo de <add>tomar</add> pildoras, y se me acabaron, y yo</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.238.jpg"/>

<fw>2</fw>

<p>pense que ya estaba bien; y me pase un día sín tomarlas y en la noche, recorde hojandome no podia ni resoyar, y casí ní ablar; recorde como á las once y media de la noche;</p>

<p> y así estube, asta las tres de la mañana, que Max fue con jess; á ablarle; que yo estaba muy mala; entonces jeess, telefonío á Doctor, á Federico porque el es el que me esta curando, y vino como á las 4, ½ de la mañana y me dío un chat, y pildoras; y pues haora estoy muy bien gracías á Diosito Lindo;</p>

<p> pero sí ya me andaba con la muerte; pero no te apenes; pues haora ya estoy bien; diejo el Doctr; que me yebaran al Hospila; no mas á darme una <del>exc</del>. exsaminasion; aber que es lo que me pasa; pues haora me ban á llevar el Sabado 6, de June sí me hayan mala mucho pues me dejaran una ó 2, semanas</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.239.jpg"/>

<fw>3</fw>

<p>no mas yo creo, pues ya me siento muy bien poreso te digo que no te vayas á peñar;</p>

<p>max ,trabajando y yo pienso que esto sera todo, muchos recuerdos para todos, de max, jesse, y family de mi tu mamá que te deseo muchas felisidades.</p>

<p>dise Kethy que sí quiere ir para ya pero que su mamá no la deja el <add>Jerry</add> anda trabajando, pues ojala y el Billy boy quisiera venirse aqui con nosotros, ya ay mucho betabel; max ande aqui con el japons; tiene 20, acres aqui esta muy serquitas de la casa;</p>

<closer>  
<salute>bueno hija te deseo siempre bien en todo tu mamá que quisiera estar estar sequitas de Uds;</salute>  
                
<signed>Jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>

<postscript><p>recive tu Bendición</p></postscript>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.236.jpg"/>
                
<opener>

<address><addrLine>Ft. Lupton, Colorado</addrLine></address>
<fw>1</fw>

<salute>Dear daughter</salute>
</opener>

<p>this letter is to greet you you, your husband and the kids. I received your Grandmother Card that Billy boy sent me. I hope you are well and feeling better.</p>
                
<p>Well, Max is working here now, and there is always work around the house.</p>

<p> But Helen told me that she is very pleased because she will have a new goddaughter, and Kathy says it’s a sister, how nice. It seems like she likes babies a lot. And she also told me that you are coming here to Fort Lupton,</p>

<p> well now I know, so I won’t rent out the rooms. You know, it took me a little while to respond to you because I have been very sick; I was truly sick. You know that I have to take pills every day and I ran out, and I</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.238.jpg"/>

<fw>2</fw>

<p>thought I was alright, and I didn’t take them for a day and that night I woke up gasping and I couldn’t even breathe, and I almost couldn’t speak. I woke up about 11:30 that night,</p>

<p> and I was like that until three in the morning when Max went to tell Jess that I was very sick. So then Jess called the doctor, Federico, because he is taking care of me. He came around about 4:30 in the morning and gave me a shot and pills, and now I’m very well, thanks to my loving God,</p>

<p> but yes I almost died. But don’t worry, because now I’m well. The doctor told them to take me to the hospital for an examination to find out what’s wrong with me, so now they’re taking me on Saturday, June 6, and if they find me really ill they will leave me there only one or two weeks</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.239.jpg"/>

<fw>3</fw>

<p>I think, because now I feel really well, so I tell you, don’t trouble yourself.</p>

<p> Max is working and I think this will be all for now. <app loc="1"><rdg>Many regards</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>Warm regards</rdg></app> <app loc="3"><rdg>Love</rdg></app> for all, from Max, Jesse and family, and from me, your mother who wishes you much happiness.</p>

<p> Kathy says that she does want to visit you but that her mom wont let her, and <add place="above">Jerry</add> is working. I wish Billy boy would like to come here with us. There is a lot of beet now. Max is <add resp="iv001">working</add> here with the Japanese; he has 20 acres that are very close to the house.</p>

<closer>  
<salute>Well daughter, I wish you always blessings in everything, your mom who wishes she could be closer to you all,</salute>  
                
<signed>Jesusita B. Torres</signed>
</closer>

<postscript><p>Receive my blessing.</p></postscript>
                
</div1>

</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>