<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L149.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert, August 14, 1962</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de William F. Schubert a Santos Baros Schubert, 14 de agosto, 1962</title>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
 <name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L149.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1962-08-14">August 14, 1962</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 typed-written page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote/>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p>Media: black ink</p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName/>
<date type="written" when="1962-08-14"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#af">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.544.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Lincoln, Nebr. Aug 14, 1962</addrLine></address>

<salute>Darling Sandra and youngsters</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>Your letters arrived this morning; so got real good service. Sure glad you, Pamela and Elizabeth wrote. Glad everything went OK on the trip. Hope Bill is working in the fields regular. I mowed the lawn this noon; am going to have to get a new blade for the mower.</p>

<p>I didn’t get anything at the auction Saturday night. Went to bed at 10:30 and didn’t get up until after 9:30A.M., Sunday. Worked Sunday washing the walls – three hours; then plastered some more and painted the places with the brush; but haven’t gotten started with the roller yet; as Monday night I went to the Reserve meeting and tonight I went to Pleasant Dale and got the brakes adjusted, oil changes and a few little things done. Stopped at the Depot on the way back to write you a note and check my work.</p>

<p>Bob has been off Monday&amp;Tuesday. It has been quiet and hope that it stays that way.</p>

<p>Weather hasn’t been bad; except today it warmed up more. Has been nice and cool nights.</p>

<p>Nothing new with me. Got a pan full of tomatoes tonight so will see if Meyers or Frappia wants any.</p>

<p>Will write later. Worked a correspondence course one night and sent the test in. Got the returnes on the last one that I wasn’t sure of; but I passed it with 82.</p>

<p>Let me know how you are doing and gives my regards to all there.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Love</salute>                    
<signed>Bill</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

 <div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.544.jpg"/>
  
  <opener>
   <address><addrLine>Lincoln, Nebraska 14 de agosto de 1962</addrLine></address>
   
   <salute>Queridos Sandra y niños:</salute>
  </opener>
  
<p>Sus cartas me llegaron hoy en la mañana, así que fue muy buen servicio. Me alegró mucho que me escribieran tú, Pamela y Elizabeth. Me alegra que no tuvieran problemas durante el viaje. Espero que Bill ya esté trabajando en el campo de forma regular. Hoy a mediodía corté el césped. Voy a tener que conseguir una nueva cuchilla para la podadora.</p>  
 
  <p>No conseguí nada en la subasta del sábado en la noche. Me fui a dormir a las 10:30 y no me levanté hasta pasadas las 9:30 A.M. del domingo. El domingo trabajé tres horas lavando las paredes y después enyesé un poco mas y pinté en algunas partes con la brocha, pero todavía no empiezo con el rodillo porque el lunes fui a la reunión de la Reserva y hoy en la noche fui a Pleasant Dale. Fui a que me ajustaran los frenos, a que me cambiaran el aceite y otras cositas pendientes. De regreso pasé por el <app loc="1" cert="high"><rdg>depósito</rdg></app> <app loc="2" cert="low"><rdg>estación.</rdg></app> para escribirte una nota y revisar mi trabajo.</p> 
 
  <p>Bob descansó el lunes y el martes. Las cosas han estado en paz y espero que así sigan. El clima no ha estado mal, excepto hoy, que hizo un poco más de calor. Hemos tenido noches bonitas y frescas. No tengo noticias. Hoy en la noche llené una sartén con tomates y voy a ver si los Meyer o los Frappia quieren algunos.</p> 
  
 <p>Te escribo mas tarde. Una noche estuve trabajando en un curso por correspondencia y mandé el examen. Recibí el resultado del último <add resp="iv001">examen</add>. No estaba seguro <add resp="iv001">del resultado</add> pero lo pasé con un 82.</p>

  
  <p>Dime cómo estás y salúdame a todos por allá.</p>
  
  <closer>
   <salute>Con amor,</salute>                    
   <signed>Bill</signed>
  </closer>
  
 </div1>
</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>