<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L143.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert, October 17, 1950</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de William F. Schubert a Santos Baros Schubert, 17 de octubre, 1950</title>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
<name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name> 
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L143.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1950-10-17">October 17, 1950</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 typed page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote/>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p>Media: black ink</p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName/>
<date type="written" when="1950-10-17"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2015" who="#af">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.532.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Camp 67</addrLine></address>
<dateline>17 Oct 1950</dateline>

<salute>My Darling Wife and Son,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>I am done typing the Reserve roster for next week so will write you a few lines then take the letters to the noon train; and hope that you’ll get this by Wednesday.  I decided to drive to Lincoln Wednesday evening then go to the Bank Thursday morning and come back on that noon train. Why don’t you call me about 9:00 P.M. Wednesday (about 8:00 your time ) or else Thursday morning. The folks number is 2-1676.  It would be nice if we could by some lots in a place that we could fix up so that we could park four or five trailers besides our own on. Maybe Brighton or one of the other little towns close to Denver. Of course if you want the lots in Ft. Lupton it’s OK with me; as we park our two trailer there any-way.</p>

<p>Last night the Special Agt and the Sheriff picked up 11 or 12 of the gandies and hauled them to jail in Falls City so I only have about 50 men today. I am going through the bunk cars and pick up the blankets. Am suppose to get meat in this P.M. so will keep busy as I still have to get the Prestone in my car, too.</p>

<p>The weather is sure fine here.  Hope that it stays this way awhile yet too.  I still don’t know anything about what this camp will do when we finish here.</p>

<p>Darling, I love you and miss you very much. Sure am lonesome so am reallylooking forward to seeing you Sunday night.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Always Yours</salute>                    
<signed>–Bill –</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>I love you both very very much</p>
</postscript>
 
</div1>

 <div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.532.jpg"/>
  
  <opener>
   <address><addrLine>Campamento 67</addrLine></address>
   <dateline>17 de Octubre de 1950</dateline>
   
   <salute>Mis queridos esposa e hijo:</salute>
  </opener>

  <p>Terminé la lista de la Reserva para la próxima semana, así que te escribiré unas líneas y después llevaré las cartas al tren de mediodía, y espero que las recibas el miércoles. Decidí ir en carro a Lincoln el miércoles por la tarde e ir al banco el jueves por la mañana y regresar en el tren de mediodía. ¿Por qué no me llamas el miércoles alrededor de las 9:00 P.M. (como las 8:00 P.M. de tu hora) o el jueves en la mañana? El número de mis papás es el 2-1676. Sería que pudiéramos comprar unos lotes en algún lugar que pudiéramos arreglar para poder estacionar otros cuatro o cinco tráileres junto al nuestro. Quizá en Brighton o alguno de los otros pueblitos cercanos a Denver. Por supuesto que si quieres los lotes en Ft. Lupton para mí está bien, porque de todas formas estacionamos ahí nuestros dos tráilers.</p>
  <p>Anoche el agente especial y el aguacil recogieron a 11 o 12 de los gandies y se los llevaron a la cárcel de Falls City, así que hoy solamente tengo unos 50 hombres. Estoy revisando todos los coches litera y recogiendo las cobijas. Se supone que voy a recibir la carne hoy en la tarde, así que voy a estar ocupado porque también tengo que ponerle el Prestone al carro.</p>
  <p>El clima esta bien. Espero que se mantenga así por un rato. Todavía no sé qué va a pasar con este campamento cuando terminemos aquí.</p>
  <p>Querida, te amo y te extraño mucho. Me siento verdaderamente solo y estoy feliz de poder verte este domingo por la noche.</p>

  <closer>
   <salute>Siempre tuyo</salute>                    
   <signed>Bill</signed>
  </closer>
  
  <postscript>
   <p>Los quiero mucho mucho</p>
  </postscript>
  
 </div1>

</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>