<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L132.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert, May 9, 1948</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de William F. Schubert a Santos Baros Schubert, 09 de mayo, 1948</title>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
 <name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name> 
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2016</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L132.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Schubert, William F.</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from William F. Schubert to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1948-05-09">May 9, 1948</date>
<extent>2 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>2 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>2 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="wfs001" medium="pen"><p>Media: blue ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p/></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName>Austin, Texas</placeName>
<date type="written" when="1948-05-09"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1948-05-09"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName>Fort Lupton, Colorado</placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2016" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#af">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.500.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Bergstrom Field</addrLine></address>
<dateline>9 May 1948</dateline>

<salute>My Darling Santos&amp;Billy –</salute>
</opener>

<p>I just finished my Sunday breakfast so am going to write; so I can mail it from town today.</p>
                
<p>Darling I am really missing you very much. Remember I love you greatly. Hope you are both well – So Billy’s cough better yet? – I am ok –</p>

<p>yesterday, I and two fellows went to Austin; went through the capitol building; saw the University of Texas; looked around the stores and went out to see the Springs’ swimming pool – The fellows I was with didn’t want to walk much so I’m going back to see the rock&amp;flower gardens – The pool at the Springs is beautiful and clean – may go swimming today. We ate dinner and supper at a nice cafe in town for very reasonable prices. There was <del>D</del> a dance at the Service Club last night so we went over but only had a few girls <del>of</del> <add>and</add> most of them came because they had dates with the permanent party men so there was nothing doing there.</p>

<p>This coming week I have four days of training then Friday we get paid&amp;check out so I’ll get in Denver Sunday morning about 8:15 – you can get Jess to drive you in to meet me or I’ll get a bus right on to Lupton, would probably be best. Anyway I’ll be with you and Billy next Sunday.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.502.jpg"/>

<fw>-2-</fw>

<p>As yet I haven’t had a letter from you as am looking for one tomorrow – Did I tell you that I am getting $1.25 a day for your Quarters, so that will be about $18.75 more than I figured I’d get. Being I have to wait part of the day to get a train when I leave I’m going to buy you and Billy some things – Was going to get them yesterday but thought I might lose or break something –</p>

<p>Sweetheart I love you very very much so remember that – take good care of your-self –</p>

<closer>
<salute>Always yours<lb/>
Your husband<lb/></salute>                    
<signed>Bill</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>Yo te amo mucho mucho</p>
</postscript>
 
</div1> 

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.498.jpg"/>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Santos B. Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>General Delivery</addrLine>
<addrLine>Ft. Lupton</addrLine>
<addrLine>Colorado</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
AUSTIN<lb/>
MAY 9<lb/>
5 PM<lb/>
1948<lb/>
TEX.<lb/>
</ab>

<pb facs="shan_l.499.jpg"/>

<ab type="postmark">
FORT LUPTON<lb/>
MAY 11<lb/>
9 PM<lb/>
1948<lb/>
COLO.<lb/>
</ab>

</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.500.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Base Aérea Bergstrom</addrLine></address>
<dateline>9 de mayo de 1948</dateline>

<salute>Mis queridos Santos y Billy –</salute>
</opener>

<p>Acabo de terminar mi desayuno dominical, así que voy a ponerme a escribir esta carta para poder enviarla hoy desde el pueblo.</p>
                
<p>Mi amor, te extraño mucho. Recuerda que te amo mucho. Espero que estén bien – ¿Mejoró la tos de Billy? – Yo estoy bien –</p>

<p>Ayer, yo y dos compañeros fuimos a Austin. Entramos al capitolio, vimos la universidad de Texas, curioseamos por las tiendas y fuimos a ver la piscina del manantial. Los compañeros con los que iba no querían caminar mucho, así que voy a volver para ver la roca y las flores del jardín. La piscina del manantial está muy bonita y muy limpia – es posible que hoy vaya a nadar. Comimos y cenamos en una cafetería del pueblo muy buena y a precio muy razonable. Anoche había un <certainty locus="name" cert="medium"><desc>juego</desc></certainty> en el club <add resp="iv001">Service Club</add> así que fuimos, pero solamente había algunas chicas y la mayoría habían ido porque ya tenían cita con los fiesteros de siempre, así que no teníamos nada que hacer allá.</p>

<p>Esta semana que viene tengo cuatro días de entrenamiento y el viernes me pagan y salgo, así que estaré en Denver el domingo en la mañana, como a las 8:15 – Puedes pedirle a Jess que te lleve en el auto para recibirme, o puedo tomar un autobús directamente hasta Lupton. Quizá sea lo mejor. De cualquier forma estaré contigo y con Billy el próximo domingo.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.502.jpg"/>

<fw>-2-</fw>

<p>A la fecha no he recibido carta tuya, así que espero una mañana – ¿Te conté que me van a dar $1.25 por día por tus <certainty locus="name" cert="medium"><desc>Quarters</desc></certainty>, así que serán $18.75 más de lo que había pensado recibir. Como tengo que esperar parte del día para tomar el tren, cuando me vaya voy a comprar algunas cosas para ti y para Billy – Las iba a comprar ayer, pero pensé que se me podían perder o quebrar o algo –</p>

<p>Cariño, te amo mucho mucho, recuérdalo – Cuídate mucho.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Siempre tuyo<lb/>
Tu esposo<lb/></salute>                    
<signed>Bill</signed>
</closer>

<postscript>
<p>I love you very very much</p>
</postscript>
 
</div1>

</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>