<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L210.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert, September 13, 1968</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de Jesusita Baros Torres a Santos Baros Schubert, 13 de septiembre, 1968</title>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="af">Faxas, Adoni A.</name>
<name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L210.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1968-09-13">September 13, 1968</date>
<extent>3 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>3 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jbt001" medium="pen"><p>Media: blue ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p/></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName/>
<date type="written" when="1968-09-13"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1968-09-15"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#af">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="#ji">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.726.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>ft Lupton Colo</addrLine></address>
<dateline>13, Sep,- 1968</dateline>

<salute>Querida hija;</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>la presente es, para Saludarte, en Compania de tu Espozo, y de los muchachos; pues te diré que recivi las post Card que me mandaste de Albuquerque Como Esta Betty, y <del>de</del> toda su famíly que dise; se acordó de mi? pues cada año me manda Cristmas y tambien recivi otra de San – Antonio Texas; se be muy bonito la Feria;</p>

<p>pues todos los días quiero escrivirles pero parese que se mi ba el dia en la nada, y como todabia estoy yendo á las Clases de Ingles pues nomas en las mañanas tego tíempo; la Helen todabía esta trabajando; pero el Markl ya esta en la escuela pues yo creo que tambíen tus muchachos estan ya en la – escuela, pues es muy bueno la escuela; yo ya estoy vieja pero,-

<pb facs="shan_l.727.jpg"/>

me gusta mucho la escuela anque se me ase trabajoso; pero me gusta mucho; ó y tambien quiero que cuando ayes ropa como para mi mi zíze es 44, de las nauguas de abajo; pues ya tu saves; y de Calzones es 42 zíze; y de bestido es tambien 42, en día de estos boy á desirle al Jess que me yebe al post offece para mandarte un sentabos para aber sí tu me ayas ropa á mí medida no te apures mucho de aquí á las Cristmas que me las mandes esta muy bueno; pues te dire que aqui ya esta reconosiendo el frío amanece muy fresca la mañana; biene calentando el dia asta el amedío día; pero yo siempre con mucho frío; ojala y me ayes ropa calíentita;</p>

<p>bueno hija pues yo creo que esto sera todo por esta ves; saludez para el Bill tu espozo y para todos los muchachos

<pb facs="shan_l.728.jpg"/>

y tu recive el mas fino Cariño de tu mamá; que te aprecio y te <add>doy</add> tu Bendicion; Diosito que nos ayude tanto á Uds, Como á Nosotros saludes de Jess y family, y de Max.</p>
 
<postscript>
<p><label>P.S.</label> contestame que tengas tiempo</p>
</postscript>

<closer>
<salute>tu mamá</salute>                    
<signed>Jesusita Torres;</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>


<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.726.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Ft. Lupton Colorado</addrLine></address>
<dateline>September 13 - 1968</dateline>

<salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>this letter is to greet you, together with your husband and the kids. Well, I’ll tell you that I received the postcards you sent me from Albuquerque. How is Betty, and how is her family? Did she remember me? Well, every year she sends me a Christmas <add resp="iv001">present</add>. And I also got another <add resp="iv001">postcard</add> from San Antonio, Texas; the fair looks beautiful.</p>

<p>I mean to write to them everyday, but it seems that the day flies by doing nothing, and since I still attending English classes, I only have
time in the mornings. Helen is still working. But Markl is already in school and I think your kids are also <app loc="1"><rdg>must also be</rdg></app> in school already. Well, school is <add resp="iv001">a</add> very good <add resp="iv001">thing</add>. I’m old but,

<pb facs="shan_l.727.jpg"/>

I like school a lot even if it’s hard, But I like it a lot. Oh, and I also want, when you find clothes like for me, my size is 44, of petticoat <app loc="1"><rdg>slip</rdg></app>, well you already know, and panties it’s size 42, and <add resp="iv001">my</add> dress
size is also size 42. One of these days I’m going to ask Jess to take me to the post office to send you some money to see if you can find clothes that fit me. No need to rush, <add resp="iv001">if</add> you can send them to me by Christmas it’s ok. Well, I will tell you that the cold is coming. Early mornings are  chilly <app loc="1" cert="high"><rdg>crisp</rdg></app>, and the day warms up around noon, but I’m always cold. Hopefully you will find me some warm clothes.</p>

<p>Well, daughter, I think this will be all for now. Regards to Bill, your husband, and to all the kids.

<pb facs="shan_l.728.jpg"/>

And receive the finest affection [much love] from your mom, who loves you, and I give you my blessing, may God help you <add resp="iv001">all</add> as well as us. Regards from Jess and family, and Max.</p>
 
<postscript>
<p><label>P.D.</label>Reply when you have time.</p>
</postscript>

<closer>
<salute>Your mom,</salute>                    
<signed>Jesusita Torres;</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.724.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>814 Pacific Ave</addrLine>
<addrLine>ft Lupton Colo. 80621</addrLine>
<addrLine>Jesusita Torres</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Santos Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>3830 “C” Street</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, Nebraska</addrLine>
<addrLine>68510</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
FORT LUPTON. CO<lb/> 
SEP 15<lb/> 
AM<lb/>
1968<lb/>
80621<lb/>
</ab>

<figure type="stamp">
<p/>
</figure>

</div1>
 
 <div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
  
  <pb facs="shan_l.726.jpg"/>
  
  <opener>
   <address><addrLine>Fort Lupton, Colorado</addrLine></address>
   <dateline>September 13, 1968</dateline>
   
   <salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
  </opener>

  <p>this letter is to greet you, together with your husband and the kids. Well, I’ll tell you that I received the postcards you sent me from Albuquerque. How is Betty, and how is her family? Did she remember me?</p>
  <p>Well, every year she sends me a Christmas <add resp="ji">postcard</add>. And I also got another <add resp="ji">postcard</add> from San Antonio, Texas; the fair looks beautiful.</p>
  <p>I mean to write to them everyday, but it seems that the day flies by doing nothing, and since I still attending English classes, I only have time in the mornings. Helen is still working. But Markl is already in school and I think your kids are also in school already. Well, school is very good. I’m old but,
  
   <pb facs="shan_l.727.jpg"/>
   I like school a lot even if it’s hard, but I like it a lot.</p>
  
  <p>Oh, and I also want, when you find clothes like for me, my size is 44, for the petticoat, well you already know, and panties it’s size 42, and my dress size is also size 42. One of these days I’m going to ask Jess to take me to the post office to send you some money to see if you can find clothes that fit me. No need to rush, if you can send them to me by Christmas it’s ok.</p>
  
  <p>Well, I will tell you that the cold is coming. Early mornings are chilly, and the day warms up around noon, but I’m always cold. Hopefully you will find me some warm clothes.</p>
  
  <p>Well, daughter, I think this will be all for now. Regards to Bill, your husband, and to all the kids.
   
   <pb facs="shan_l.728.jpg"/>
   
   And receive the finest affection from your mom, who loves you, and I give you my blessing, may God help you as well as us. Regards from Jess and family, and Max.</p>
  
  <postscript>
   <p><label>P.D.</label>Reply when you have time</p>
  </postscript>
  
  <closer>
   <salute>Your mom,</salute>                    
   <signed>Jesusita Torres</signed>
  </closer>
  
 </div1>
 
  
  
 
 
</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>