<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L022.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from Guadalupe Flemate to Jesusita Baros Torres, December 20, 1940</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de Guadalupe Flemate a Jesusita Baros Torres, 20 de diciembre, 1940</title>
<author>Flemate, Guadalupe</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="iv002">Velázquez, Isabel</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L022.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Guadalupe Flemate</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Guadalupe Flemate to Jesusita Baros Torres</title>
<date when="1940-12-20">December 20, 1940</date>
<extent>2 pages and envelope</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>2 hand-written pages and envelope</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>2 pages and envelope
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="gf001" medium="pencil"><p>Media: lead/graphite</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p/></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="gf001">Flemate, Guadalupe</persName>
<placeName>Juchipila, Zacatecas, México</placeName>
<date type="written" when="1940-12-20"/>
<date type="postmarked" when="1940-12-20"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName>Fort Lupton, Colorado</placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#iv002">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.146.jpg"/>
                  
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Juchipila</addrLine></address>
<dateline>20 de deciembre de 1940</dateline>

<salute>Sra Eliboria Flemate</salute>
</opener>
          
<p>mi muy estimada hermana te dirijo la presente para saludarte y al mismo tiempo para desirte que resebí tu carta  en la cual me dises que estas bien tu y tus hijos la que de mi se despide me deja bien gracias a dios pues hermana as de dispensarme la tardanza en contestar tu carta en ella benia un peso y estoy resebida del de tu encargo no tengas pendiente comadre en esta te digo que mi tia Gracia esta en agonía te mando decir para que rueges a dios por ella que es muy difícil su alivio llo creo que ala hotra carta tedigo de su muerte comadre me da mucha pena contigo que te contesto tus cartas a los dos otres meses pero te boy a desir salgo tan cansada del trabajo que tengo <unclear reason="illegible">ya</unclear> me boy a descansar y seban pasando los dias y lla cuando menos acuerdo lla se paso el tiempo si vieras que estar atendiendo a los clientes unos porque seban hotros porque llegan la cosa es de que no descanza uno las desveladas cuando llegan en la noche señora un cuarto cuando uno esta mas agusto en su cama alla ba uno a dar camas llo te digo comadre que llame canse de este trabajo pero que ago pues

<pb facs="shan_l.148.jpg"/>

Si no lo hago asi de trabajar en mi hotel de ay saco para la nanutencion tengo dos criadas julia nuestra hermana y otra en el quiaser de la cosina pues hermana llo te aseguro que si no debiera por dios que lla no trabajaba pero lo que saco delas tieritas que tocaron <unclear reason="illegible">Irma</unclear> para pagar las drogas que me che cuando peliamos llo y Camilo mi segundo marido que dios no le tome en cuenta al muy ingrato lo que me esploto me alcanzo la perdida con ese marido con dos mil pesos lla no mas debo 800 pesos a mauro quesada bueno hermana lla te platice los sufrimientos de la vida que si te platico lo que e sufrido es una ystoria mi vida</p>
                
<closer><salute>resibe saludes de julia nuestra hermana bieras ques una mujer buena para ella todo es temporal dales mis recuerdos a Santos a jesus y tu recibe los mas finos recuerdos de tu hermana quien no te holbida bueno asta la vuelta de correo</salute>

<signed> Guadalupe Flemate</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.144.jpg"/>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Sra.</addrLine>
<addrLine>Jesusita Baros</addrLine>
<addrLine>P.O. box 481</addrLine>
<addrLine>Fort Lupton. Colo</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
JUCHIPILA<lb/>
20.DIC.4017<lb/>
ZAC<lb/>
</ab>

<figure type="stamp">
<p/>
</figure>

<pb facs="shan_l.145.jpg"/>

<ab type="note">
Si no es entregada debuelbase a<lb/>
Guadalupe Flemate<lb/>
Hotel Saragosa<lb/>
Juchipila<lb/>
</ab>

</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.146.jpg"/>
                  
<opener>
<address><addrLine>Juchipila</addrLine></address>
<dateline>December 20, 1940</dateline>

<salute>Mrs. Eliboria Flemate</salute>
</opener>
          
<p>My highly esteemed sister, I write this letter to greet you and to let you know that I received your letter, in which you tell me that you and your children are well. This <add resp="iv001">letter</add> leaves me well, thank God.</p>

<p>Well, sister, you will forgive the delay in my response. In it I found one peso, and I confirm its receipt. Don’t worry about your request, comadre. In this letter I tell you that my aunt Gracia is in <app loc="1"><rdg>agony</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>dying</rdg></app>. I’m letting you know so that you may pray to God on her behalf because her recovery is <app loc="1"><rdg>very difficult</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>unlikely</rdg></app> I think I will tell you about her death in <app loc="1"><rdg>the</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>my</rdg></app> next letter. Comadre, I am very embarrassed <add resp="iv001">with you</add> because I answer your letters two or three months later, but I will tell you something: I am so tired when I finish work that I go <add resp="iv001">directly</add> to rest and the days keep going by and when I come to notice time has flown by. Let me tell you that taking care of clients, some because they leave, other because they arrive, the thing is that you don’t rest. All the late nights,‘miss, a room’, just when you are most comfortable in your own bed, you have to get up to assign <add resp="iv001">other people's</add> beds. I tell you, comadre, that I’m tired of this work I do, because

<pb facs="shan_l.148.jpg"/>

If I don’t do it, if I don’t work in my hotel, there’s where I earn <add resp="iv001">money</add> to support myself. I have two servants in charge of kitchen duties: Julia, our sister, and another one. Well, sister, I tell you that if I were not in debt, by God I would not work anymore, but what I earn from the <app loc="1" type="diminutive"><rdg>land</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>small amount</rdg></app> that were <app loc="1" cert="low"><rdg>left to</rdg></app> <app loc="2" cert="low"><rdg>goes to</rdg></app> <app loc="3" cert="low"><rdg>should go to</rdg></app> Irma  paying the debt that I was left with after fighting with Camilo, my second husband. May God not judge him, the ingrate, on the way he exploited me. With that husband the loss amounted to two thousand pesos. Now I only owe 800 pesos to Mauro Quesada. Well, sister, now I’ve told you about all my life’s suffering. If I were to tell you <add resp="iv001">all</add> that I have suffered, my life is <add resp="iv001">quite</add> a story.</p>
                
<closer><salute>Receive regards from our sister Julia, let me tell you that she is a good woman. For her, everything is temporary. Give my regards to Santos, to Jesus, and receive the finest regards from your sister who does not forget you. Well, <app loc="1"><rdg>until the mail comes</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>until your next letter</rdg></app> <app loc="3"><rdg>until my next letter</rdg></app></salute>

<signed>Guadalupe Flemate</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>