<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L224.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Santos Baros Schubert to William F. Schubert, October 12, 1950</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Santos Baros Schubert a William F. Schubert, 12 de octubre, 1950</title>
<author>Baros Schubert, Santos</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="ji">Isasi, Jennifer</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2017</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L224.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Schubert, Santos</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Santos Baros Schubert to William F. Schubert</title>
<date when="1950-10-10">October 12, 1950</date>
<extent>1 envelope and 4 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 hand-written envelope and 4 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>1 envelope and 4 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote><p>Media:</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1950-10-12"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="wfs001">Schubert, William F.</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017" who="#sbg">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2017" who="#ji">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.803.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>Oct. 12, 1950</dateline>
<dateline>Thurs.</dateline>

<salute>Dearest Bill,</salute>
</opener>

<p>I went to post office &amp; didn&#39;t find any mail.</p>
<p>Will write you what little information I gathered about the lots. Well, yesterday mother
and I went to see the lots on different places. I saw 4 lots that I like. They&#39;re on a corner.
Mother wants two &amp; I thought we could <add place="above">buy</add> the other two. I
think that at least two would be best for us - being that we&#39;ve two trailers. Anyway we
went to see the man that&#39;s in charge of them lots. Says they cost $125.00 each lot - <hi rend="underline">cash</hi>.And $150.00 if you buy on payments. He sent me to Town Hall or City Hall to inquire
about <add place="above">them</add> lots, cause I heard that there was alot of red tape to them. And I&#39;d</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.804.jpg"/>

<p>have to go to Greeley to get the abstract to the lots. And I don&#39;t know if these lots are
outside city limits or inside. About the sewer I don&#39;t know much - only that it costs
$12.50 to tap. I think you pay that to the city. I was suppose to find out about these things
this afternoon but I was too <add place="above">late</add> at the City Hall, close at 3:PM
I&#39;ll go again tomorrow morning. Oh yes, everybody says the lights won&#39;t amount too
much.</p>
<p>Listen if you&#39;re thinking of us spending the Winter here you better not sell the old trailer.
We can rent it. And if we buy these lots you can send me my postal notes from the bank.
We can buy them with my money.</p>
<pb/>
<p>Billy caught a cold. He&#39;s helping mother bring in some wood. He also helped her chase
the chickens into the chicken house. He likes Max better than mother.</p>
<p>This is all for this time.</p>
<p>I&#39;ll write again.</p>
<p>Don&#39;t forget we love U. And we&#39;re lonesome for you.</p>
<p>Faithfully yours,</p>
<p>Sandra</p>
<lb/>
<p>Fri. A.M.</p>
<p>Am at post office. Came to City Hall. Mr. Carlson told <add place="above">me</add> there&#39;s no back taxes on them lots. It&#39;s inside city limits. There&#39;s a sewer there and it costs
$12.50 to tap $20.00 for the water a year. To <del type="strike">com</del> hook up the pipes
to the trailers, that costs extra. And he says that eventually you would have to build a</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.805.jpg"/>

<p>house there. And no trailers are allowed here unless they&#39;re hooked up to the sewer. I
have to go to court house in Greeley to find out about the abstract. I think there&#39;s no red
tape to them. Well, shall we buy them or not?</p>
<p>If we do you better send me my money that I&#39;ve at the Post office in Denver.
Billy is here with me. Have to go to Safeway’s.</p>
<p>Be sure &amp; answer soon &amp; let me know what you think.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Lovingly yours,</salute>
<signed>Sandra</signed>
</closer>

</div1>


<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.803.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>12 de octubre de 1950</dateline>
<dateline>Jueves.</dateline>

<salute>Queridísimo Bill,</salute>
</opener>

<p>Fui al correo y no encontré carta.</p>
<p>Te escribo con la poca información que tengo sobre los lotes. Bueno, anoche mamá y yo fuimos a ver los lotes en lugares distintos. Vi cuatro lotes que me gustaron. Están en una esquina. Mamá quiere dos y pensé que nosotros podíamos comprar los otros dos. Creo que por lo menos dos sería lo mejor para nosotros, porque tenemos dos trailers. En fin, fuimos a ver al hombre que está a cargo de los lotes. Dice que cuestan $125.00 cada uno –al contado. Y $150.00 a plazos. Me mandó al ayuntamiento <app loc="1"><rdg>gobierno de la ciudad</rdg></app>a preguntar por ellos, porque oí que
venían con mucho trámite burocrático, y que tendría que</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.804.jpg"/>

<p>ir a Greeley para pedir el título de propiedad de los lotes. Y no sé si esos lotes están dentro o fuera de los límites de la ciudad. No sé mucho acerca del drenaje –solo que cuesta $12.50 para conectarse. Creo que se le paga a la ciudad. Iba a averiguar todo eso hoy en la tarde, pero llegué tarde al ayunatamiento <app loc="1"><rdg>gobierno de la ciudad</rdg></app>, cierra a las 3:00 pm. Iré ora vez mañana en la mañana. Ah sí, todo mudo dice que la luz no sería muy cara.</p>
<p>Mira, si estás pensando que pasemos el invierno aquí mejor no vendas el tráiler viejo. Podríamos rentarlo. Y si compramos estos lotes puedes mandarme mis notas postales del banco. Podemos comprarlos con mi dinero.</p>

<pb/>

<p>Billy se resfrió. Le está ayudando a mamá a meter la leña. También le ayudó a corretear a las gallinas para meterlas al gallinero. Le cae mejor Max que mamá.</p>
<p>Esto es todo por hoy.</p>
<p>Volveré a escribirte.</p>
<p>No te olvides de que te queremos y te extrañamos mucho.</p>
<p>Fielmente tuya <app loc="1"><rdg>tu fiel esposa</rdg></app></p>
<p>Sandra</p>
<lb/>
<p>Viernes por la mañana</p>
<p>Vine al ayuntamiento <app loc="1"><rdg>gobierno de la ciudad</rdg></app>. El señor Carlson me dijo que no se deben impuestos por esos lotes. Están dentro de los límites de la ciudad. Hay drenaje y cuesta $12.50
conectarse y $20.00 al año por el agua. Se paga extra por conectar la tubería hasta los trailers. Dice que eventualmente se tendría que construir ahí</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.805.jpg"/>

<p>una casa. Y que no se permiten trailers a menos de que estén conectados al drenaje. Necesito ir a la corte de Greeley para preguntar por el título. Creo que no hay problemasburocráticos con esos lotes. Bueno, ¿los compramos o no?</p>
<p>Si los vamos a comprar es mejor que me mandes mi dinero que está en la oficina de correos de Denver. Billy está aquí conmigo. Tengo que ir al Safeway</p>
<p>Responde pronto y dime qué opinas.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Amorosamente tuya,</salute>
<signed>Sandra</signed>
</closer>

</div1>

<div1 type="envelope">

<pb facs="shan_l.801.jpg"/>

<ab type="address">
<address>
<addrLine>Mr. William F. Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>Camp 67</addrLine>
<addrLine>Rulo, Nebraska</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>

<ab type="postmark">
FORT LUPTON<lb/> 
OCT 13<lb/>
5:30 PM<lb/>
1950<lb/>
COLO<lb/>
</ab>

<figure type="stamp">
<p></p>
</figure>

<pb facs="shan_l.802.jpg"/>

<ab type="return">
<address>
<addrLine>Mrs. Sandra B. Schubert</addrLine>
<addrLine>P. O. Box 681</addrLine>
<addrLine>Ft. Lupton, Colo.</addrLine>
</address>
</ab>


</div1>
</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>