<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="shan_L072.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main" xml:lang="en">Letter from Josephine Montoya to Santos Baros Schubert, August 1, 1942</title>
<title type="main" xml:lang="es">Carta de Josephine Montoya a Santos Baros Schubert, 1 de agosto, 1942</title>
<author>Montoya, Josephine</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="km">Mendell, Kate</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L072.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note/></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Josephine Montoya</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Josephine Montoya to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1942-08-01">August 1, 1942</date>
<extent>1 page</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno/>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>1 typed page</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support/>
<extent>1 page
<dimensions unit="mm"><height/><width/></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p/></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc>
<handNote/>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p>Media: black ink</p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin/>
<provenance/>
<acquisition/>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p/>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p/>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term/>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jm001">Montoya, Josephine</persName>
<placeName>Socorro, New Mexico</placeName>
<date type="written" when="1942-08-01"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName/>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#km">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.212.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>P.O. Box LL</dateline>
<add>Socorro, N. M.</add>
<add>August 1, 1942</add>

<address><addrLine>Dearest Pal:</addrLine></address>

<salute>Well, Santos, I guess it is about time that I should answer your letter being that if I leave it a long time going unanswered I will soon forget about it. Well, we are all just fine thanks to God and hope that you are the same.</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>Didn’t have much to do in the office so I thought I would answer some of my correspondence. I sure have been doing a lot of answering now. I just answered a letter to Bennie and another to Johnnie and Joe, of course. It seems like as if Talley is not going into the army any more, at least, I hope he isn’t as he is going to take a defense job pretty soon and I would much prefer for him to take this job than to go as a volunteer. I talked him out of it when I went home and I guesshe took my advice.</p>

<p>Oh, Santos, aren’t you going to be here for the fiestas? Well, I guess it is too late for you to think of even coming as they are already here. I don’t think I’m going over. I would much rather stay here in Socorro and spend the week-end reading as I always do whenever I stay here. I remember all the fun we two used to have at the fiestas - - remember. Anyway if I go I won’t have any fun as there are nobody left to enjoy your self with. Gee, I sure felt bad when I received a letter from Joe yester-day from New York. Can you beat that? They sure took him far away from me. It’s a good thing he came over to see me for the Fourth. Heck, I’m sure tired of this war business but there isn’t much you can do about it so we better keep our chin up and take it as it comes. Now that the world was changing for me something like this had to happen. We are expecting Johnnie now for the fiestas of course I won’t be home but they are planning on coming over to Socorro. I told them to although I don’t know whether they will come or not. I Hope they will cause now that Annie left I sure feel like a lonely cow with nobody on my side. Especially here cause all the girls act so stuck-up. But I’ll have to face life some way or another.</p>

<p>In your letter you ask me of Alex, Joe’s brother. Well, he is still around. I saw him last Saturday when I went home. He is still the same old guy. I think he will be drafted pretty soon though he’s got a swell job. He works for the Santa Fe Shops so he gets good dough.</p>

<p>It won’t be long when they will be drafting us pretty soon. Huh - - well, I don’t think I will mind it so much as I would much rather be some place else than in this dumb-founded town. I think I have said more than I expected to so here I close my letter until I hear from you.</p>

<p>Has Leonor written you? I haven’t see her since I went over to her house.</p>

<closer>     
<salute>REGARDS TO ALL</salute>   
<add>P..S..</add>            
<add>I'm still waiting for</add>
<add>that promised future</add>
<add>of yours.</add>

<signed>A Long but Not Forgotten Friend,</signed>
<add>Josephine Montoya</add>
<add>P.O. Box LL</add>
<add>Socorro, N.M.</add>
</closer>

<postscript><p>Excuse my typewriting.</p></postscript>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.212.jpg"/>
                
<opener>
<dateline>P.O. Box LL</dateline>
<add>Socorro, N. M.</add>
<add>1o de agosto de 1942</add>

<address><addrLine>Querida amiga:</addrLine></address>

<salute>Bueno Santos, supongo que ya es hora de contestar tu carta, porque si la dejo sin respuesta mucho tiempo se me va a olvidar. Bueno, nosotros estamos bien gracias a Dios, y ojalá que ustedes también.</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>No tenía mucho qué hacer en la oficina, así que se me ocurrió ponerme a responder mi correspondencia. He estado <app loc="1"><rdg>respondiendo</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>escribiendo</rdg></app> <app loc="1"><rdg>mucho</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>muchas cartas</rdg></app>. Acabo de responderle una carta a Bennie y otra a Johnnie y a Joe, desde luego. Parece que Talley ya no va entrar al ejército. Al menos eso espero, porque va aceptar un trabajo en <app loc="1"><rdg>la defensa</rdg></app> <app loc="2"><rdg>el departamento de defensa</rdg></app> dentro de poco, y yo prefiero que acepte ese trabajo en lugar de que se vaya como voluntario. Lo convencí cuando fui a mi casa y supongo que tomó mi consejo.</p>

<p>Ay Santos, ¿no vas a estar aquí para las fiestas? Bueno, supongo que es demasiado tarde para que pienses en venir, porque ya están aquí. Creo que yo no voy a ir. Prefiero quedarme aquí en Socorro y pasar el fin de semana leyendo como hago siempre que me quedo aquí. Recuerdo cómo nos divertíamos durante las fiestas - - ¿te acuerdas? De todas maneras, si voy no me voy a divertir porque no queda nadie con quien disfrutarlas. Híjole, me sentí muy mal ayer que recibí
carta de Joe desde Nueva York. ¿Puedes creerlo? Se lo llevaron muy lejos de mí. Fue bueno que viniera a verme el cuatro de julio. Caray, ya estoy cansada de todo este asunto de la guerra, pero no hay mucho que podamos hacer, así que hay que mantener el ánimo arriba y tomar las cosas como vengan. Justo cuando el mundo empezaba a cambiar para mí tuvo que pasar esto. Esperamos a Johnnie ahora para las fiestas. Claro que yo no voy a estar en casa, pero están planeando venir a Socorro. Les dije que vinieran, pero no estoy segura si van a venir o no. Espero que sí, porque ahora que se fue Annie me siento como vaca solitaria sin nadie de mi lado. Especialmente aquí, porque las muchachas son muy presumidas. Pero tendré que enfrentar la vida de alguna manera u otra.</p>

<p>En tu carta me preguntas por Alex, el hermano de Joe. Bueno, todavía anda por aquí. Lo vi el sábado que fui a la casa. Sigue siendo el mismo. Creo lo van a reclutar dentro de poco, aunque tiene un trabajo buenísimo. Trabaja para las tiendas en Santa Fe y gana mucha lana.</p>

<p>Dentro de poco nos van a reclutar a nosotras ¿verdad? Bueno, no me molestaría tanto, porque preferiría estar en cualquier otro lugar que en este pueblo tonto. Creo que he dicho más de lo qu esperaba, así que aquí cierro mi carta hasta que sepa de ti.</p>

<p>¿Te ha escrito Leonor? No la he visto desde fui a su casa.</p>

<closer>     
<salute>SALUDOS PARA TODOS</salute>   
<add>P.D.</add>            
<add>Todavía sigo esperando</add>
<add>tu foto tan prometida.</add>

<signed>Una vieja pero nunca olvidada amiga,</signed>
<add>Josephine Montoya</add>
<add>P.O. Box LL</add>
<add>Socorro, N.M.</add>
</closer>

<postscript><p>Disculpa mi mecanografía.</p></postscript>
                
</div1>

</body>
        
<back/>
</text>
</TEI>