<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xml:id="shan_L030.meta">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert, July 10, 1964</title>
<title type="main">Carta de Jesusita Baros Torres a Santos Baros Schubert, 10 de julio, 1964</title>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<principal xml:id="iv001">Velázquez, Isabel</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
<name xml:id="jda">Avelar, Janette D.</name>
<name xml:id="iv002">Velázquez, Isabel</name>
<name xml:id="sbg">Garcia, Sarita B.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2015</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Family Letters: An analysis of the Personal Correspondence of a Mexican American Family in Western Colorado and Eastern Nebraska in the First Half of the 20th Century</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Department of Modern Languages and Literatures</name>
 <address>
<addrLine>1111 Oldfather Hall</addrLine>
<addrLine>660 N 12th</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
<addrLine>modlang2@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-0315</addrLine>
</address>
<idno>shan_L030.meta</idno>
<availability>
<p>COPYRIGHT STATEMENT TO GO HERE</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
<notesStmt><note></note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<author>Baros Torres, Jesusita</author>
<title level="m" type="main">Letter from Jesusita Baros Torres to Santos Baros Schubert</title>
<date when="1964-07-10">July 10, 1964</date>
<extent>3 pages</extent>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository>Shanahan Collection</repository>
<idno></idno>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<p>3 hand-written pages</p>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc>
<support></support>
<extent>3 pages
<dimensions unit="mm"><height></height><width></width></dimensions>
</extent>
<condition>
<p></p></condition>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
<handDesc hands="1">
<handNote xml:id="h01" scribe="jbt001" medium="pen"><p>Media: black ink</p></handNote>
</handDesc>
<typeDesc>
<typeNote><p></p></typeNote>
</typeDesc>
</physDesc>
<history><origin></origin>
<provenance></provenance>
<acquisition></acquisition>
</history>
</msDesc>
                
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction>
<p></p>
</correction>
<normalization>
<p></p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="people">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="places">
<term></term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
<correspDesc>
<correspAction type="sentBy">
<persName xml:id="jbt001">Baros Torres, Jesusita</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
<date type="written" when="1964-07-10"/>
</correspAction>
<correspAction type="deliveredTo">
<persName xml:id="sbs001">Baros Schubert, Santos</persName>
<placeName></placeName>
</correspAction>
<correspContext>
<ref type="prev" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
<ref type="next" target="shan">Letter from x to y, date</ref>
</correspContext> 
</correspDesc>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2015" who="#jda">Initial Encoding</change>
<change when="2014" who="#iv002">Transcription</change>
            
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
            
<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="es">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.096.jpg"/>
   
<opener>

<dateline>Ft, Lupton Colo</dateline>                    
<add>July 10, -64</add>
</opener>
           
<p>Qerida hija la precente es para saludarlos á todos esperando que esten bien asi como nosotros estamos pues te dire que no le é contestado á la Pamela; porque como la Kathy me ase las cartas en ingles y ella esta trabajando, pues no tiene tiempo, los Domingos  no trabaga, pero pues se lebanta muy tarde, y no la miro; </p>
<p> pues Jess es el que me lleva á misa, y me dise que esta durmiendo, pues en la tarde yo creo que se ba a pasiar, con su nuvio; y poreso no le é contestado á la Pamela; pero dile que me </p>

<pb facs="shan_l.098.jpg"/>

<p> siga escribiendo; lla que tu no me escribes; </p>

<p> bueno te platicare que vino la Sra Bossor, tu sabes á vesitar á Helen dice que esta muy enferma, sí esta muy muy flaca;</p>

<p>dicen Helen que esta enferma de la zangre, tiene la zangre anemia; después que se fue de aquí entro al Hospital; yo é estado bien hora tengo que ir al Hospital asta en Octubre día 12; ya me quitaron los chats; estoy no mas tomando las tablets; y la dieta; pero me siento muy bien Gracias á Diosito que á sido tan bueno con nosotros; ojalá y tú tambíen bien pues todos los días le pido ayuda tanto para ti como á tu esposo, y familia;</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.099.jpg"/>

<p>bueno hija pues yo creo que esto será todo por esta ves siempre te digo que no se olviden de nosotros, muchos recuerdos para Pamela en especial; para ella. y deveras que sí le agradesco que me escriba yo le entiendo muy bien bueno siempre reciví tu Bendíción que yo te síempre</p>

<closer><salute>tu mamá</salute>        
<signed>Jesusita Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

<div1 type="letter" xml:lang="en">
                
<pb facs="shan_l.096.jpg"/>
   
<opener>

<dateline>Ft, Lupton Colo</dateline>                    
<add>July 10, -64</add>

<salute>Dear daughter,</salute>
</opener>
                
<p>This letter is to greet you all, hoping that you are well, like we are.</p>

<p>I will tell you that I haven’t replied to Pamela because Kathy writes the letters in English for me and she is working, so she doesn’t have time. She doesn’t work on Sunday, but she gets up very late and I don’t see her. Jess is the one who takes me to mass and he tells me that she is sleeping, and well, in the afternoon I think she goes out with her boyfriend, and that is why I haven’t answered Pamela, but tell her to

<pb facs="shan_l.098.jpg"/>

keep writing, since you don’t write to me. Well, I will tell you that Mrs. Bossor came to visit Helen. <app loc="1" cert="high"><rdg>She</rdg></app> <app loc="2" cert="high"><rdg>Helen</rdg></app> <app loc="3" cert="high"><rdg>Mrs. Bossor</rdg></app> says that she is very ill. And yes, she is very, very thin; Helen says that she has an illness in the blood, she has anemia blood. After she left here she entered the hospital. I’ve been well. I don’t have to go to the hospital until October, on the 12th. They suspended the shots, I’m only taking the tablets; and the diet, but I feel ver well, thank God, who has been so good to us. I hope he is also good to you, because I ask his help for you and your husband and your family every day.</p>

<pb facs="shan_l.099.jpg"/>

<p>well daugther, I think this will be all for now. As always, I tell you not to forget us. Many regards to Pamela, especially to her. I trully appreciate that she writes to us, I understand <add resp="iv001">her letters</add> very well. Well, as always, receive my blessing, that I always </p>

<closer><salute>Your mom,</salute>        
<signed>Jesusita Torres</signed>
</closer>
                
</div1>

</body>
        
<back></back>
</text>
</TEI>
